Finding Aid for Russell Curtis Barnes papers, 1920-1978
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Russell Curtis Barnes papers 1920-1978
Barnes, Russell Curtis, 1897-
7 linear feet
858 Aa 2
Correspondent with the Detroit News, director of the Psychological Warfare Division, Supreme Headquarters, Allied Forces, during World War II. Scrapbooks with clippings of newspaper articles; copies of propaganda leaflets directed to German soldiers and civilians during the war; reports, correspondence with family, and printed matter relating to war-time service; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from Russell and Mrs. Barnes (donor no. 6571 ) in multiple accession 1980-1991.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Russell Curtis Barnes was born in Huntington, Indiana on August 31, 1897, the son of James F. and Lucy A. (Stewart) Barnes. There he attended high school and worked for the Huntington Press before entering the University of Michigan. During his years at the University, Barnes was active in a variety of student activities including working for the Michigan Daily, the Gargoyle, and the Wolverine and writing the book and lyrics for two Michigan Union Opera productions. In addition, he acted as campus correspondent for the Detroit News. In 1920 he received his A.B. degree in economics.
Immediately after graduation Barnes began full-time work at the Detroit News. During the years 1920-1925 he reported from the Detroit, Lansing and Washington news bureaus. In 1925 he was assigned to Paris as foreign correspondent. While there he met Constance Ingalls and they were married in 1927.
Barnes returned to the U.S. in 1931, again assigned to cover stories in Detroit, Lansing and Washington. During this time he also became a radio commentator on Detroit News Station WWJ. In 1937 he organized the Detroit Committee on Foreign Relations and became its first secretary.
Barnes was made London correspondent in 1941 and reported on the effects of the war there for the Detroit News, WWJ, and for the North American Newspaper Alliance. However, he was recalled for assignments in the U.S. before the end of the year.
In 1942 Barnes received a leave of absence from the Detroit News to join the Office of War Information in New York. Here he compiled war news stories and made overseas broadcasts for the Voice Of America. By February of 1943 he was appointed Special Assistant to the American Minister to Egypt and General Representative of the Overseas Operations Branch of the OWI. In this capacity Barnes acted as one of the two press officers allowed to attend the Cairo and Teheran conferences of Allied leaders. In 1944 he became chief of the OWI, Mediterranean Theater and director of the Psychological Warfare Bureau, Allied Forces Headquarters. He commanded over 4,000 men in the preparation and dissemination of propaganda in preparation for the Allied invasion in August 1944. In addition, he was responsible for the overall distribution of news in print and on radio in Italy, North Africa and the Middle East. After his resignation from the post in 1945 he received the War Department's Exceptional Civilian Service Emblem.
Rejoining the Detroit News as foreign correspondent, Barnes sent back stories from numerous foreign countries and covered the Paris Peace Conference and other meetings of national leaders before returning to New York as United Nations correspondent. In 1953 he returned to Detroit to become the newspaper's foreign news analyst until his retirement in 1970. During that time and since his retirement Barnes has been active as a lecturer on politics and foreign affairs at Oakland Community College and for a variety of community organizations.
The Russell Barnes papers span the years 1920-1978. The bulk of the material concerns the period 1941-1953, the years Barnes spent as foreign correspondent for the Detroit News and the three-year interval during which he served in the Office of War Information.
The collection consists primarily of scrapbooks of his news stories, OWT leaflets, collected propaganda, and letters which he sent to his wife Constance, and, less frequently, to his children, Jeannot (Lucie Jeanne) and Jamie (John James Ingalls) while overseas and in New York. The most detailed description of his professional activities can be found in the letters he wrote during the months at the OWI in New York. He discusses the OWI personnel, its reorganization and the conflict with the OSS. The letters from the OWI Cairo and Algiers contain lively discussions of local customs and the rigors of life there, but are constrained by war-time censorship and thus shed less light than might be expected on his role as PWB director. The letters written while he covered the U.N. sometimes reflect the tense atmosphere there and the pressure brought to bear upon newsmen to take a stand on the issues they report. Barnes also discusses the power struggle in the Detroit Foreign Policy Association.
Subjects:
Detroit news.; Journalists--Michigan--Detroit.; American newspapers--Michigan--Detroit.; Propaganda.; Psychological warfare.; Allied Forces. Supreme Headquarters. Psychological Warfare Division.; World War, 1939-1945.; Barnes, Russell Curtis, 1897-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Algiers (Algeria); Allied Forces. Supreme Headquarters. Psychological Warfare Division.; Banquets.; Barnes, Russell Curtis, 1897-; Cairo Conference (1943); Children--1906.; Classrooms.; Clubhouses--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Coughlin, Charles E. (Charles Edward), 1891-1979.; Detroit news.; Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971.; Egypt.; Fraternities and sororities.; Huntington (Ind.); Italy.; Journalists--Michigan--Detroit.; Phi Delta Theta Fraternity. Michigan Alpha Chapter (University of Michigan); Reporters.; Teheran Conference (1943); University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.; World War, 1939-1945.
Genre Terms:
Albums.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Scrapbooks containing clippings of news stories
  - 1920s (Box 1)
  - 1928 (Box 1)
  - 1928-1929 (Box 1)
  - 1929-1930 (Box 1)
  - 1931-1941 (Box 1)
  - 1941-1946 (Box 2)
  - 1946-1947 (Box 2)
  - 1947-1948 (Box 2)
  - January-December 1946 (Box 3)
  - December 1946-March 1948 (Box 3)
  - March 1948-July 1949 (Box 3)
  - July 1949-November 1950 (Box 3)
  - December 1950-February 1952 (Box 4)
  - March 1952-February 1953 (Box 4)
  - March-December 1953 (Box 4)
  - December 1953-November 1954 (Box 4)
  - Loose clippings November 1954-1970s, 35 folders (Box 5)
- Psychological Warfare Bureau, Headquarters Fifth Army
  - Propaganda leaflets directed to German soldiers and civilians, 1 folders; 2 volumes (Box 6)
  - Pro-Russian propaganda (Box 6)
  - Chinese and Japanese language propaganda (Box 6)
  - Pro-German propaganda (Box 6)
  - Polish language propaganda (Box 6)
  - Italian language propaganda (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous foreign language material (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous World War II printed material, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Speeches,1945 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Functions and activities of the Psychological Warfare Bureau (Box 6)
  - World War II miscellanea, 2 folders (Box 7)
- Correspondence from Barnes to his wife and children
  - August 1941-March 1943 (Box 7)
  - Early 1943 undated (Box 7)
  - April 1943-December 1944 (Box 7)
  - January 1945-September 1945 (Box 7)
  - January 1946-June 1946 (Box 7)
  - July 1946-January 1947 (Box 7)
  - December 1946-January 1947 undated (Box 7)
  - March 1947-December 1947 (Box 7)
  - January 1948-April 1948 (Box 7)
  - May 1948-August 1948 (Box 7)
  - August 1950-September 1950 (Box 7)
  - October 1950-December 1950 (Box 7)
  - January 1951-May 1951 (Box 7)
  - July 1951-October 1951 (Box 7)
  - March 1953-August 1953, July 5, 1978 (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous
  - Miscellaneous and undated correspondence (Box 7)
  - Incoming correspondence 1925-1973 (Box 7)
  - Musical Activities at the University of Michigan (Box 7)
  - Organizational Membership Materials (Box 7)
  - Speeches and Speaking Engagements (Box 7)
  - Clippings about Barnes (Box 7)
  - Photograph album, 1943 with photos of RB and other dignitaries participating at conferences in Cairo and Teheran, including a trip to Italy (Box 7)
  - Photographs, 3 folders (Box 7)
    (include portraits; class photographs, group photographs, and other photographs illustrative of class activities at schools in Huntington, Indiana, and at the University of Michigan)